{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This city constructed a paved road used to transport boats overland called the Diolkos. A\ndispute between this city and its colony of Corcyra was a cause of the Peloponnesian War.\nCypselid rulers of this city included its second tyrant, Periander. Capitals bedecked with\nacanthus leaves characterized this city’s namesake order of columns. For 10 points, name this\nancient Greek city located on a namesake isthmus.",
      "answer": [
        "Corinth",
        "Korinthos"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One holder of this title boasted that his descendants would rule for 10,000 generations, though\ncounting him they ruled for only two. That holder of this title followed Legalist precepts while\nburning subversive books and died after taking mercury pills in search of immortality. For 10\npoints, name this title taken by Qin Shi Huang and later used by leaders of the Han dynasty.",
      "answer": [
        "emperor of China",
        "huangdi",
        "di"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Pope Leo I convinced Attila the Hun not to perform this kind of action. This kind of action\nwas done by Gauls following the 390 BC Battle of the Allia. In 410 AD, Alaric led an army of\nVisigoths in performing this action, which St. Jerome identified as the effective end of the\nEmpire. For 10 points, identify this action in which the \"eternal city\" is pillaged.",
      "answer": "sack of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city once turned away foreign help during an earthquake in fear of contaminating its\nsocial system, which involved events such as the \"krypteia\" (pr. crip-TAY-uh), a ritual\ndeclaration of war on its slave class, the helots (pr. HELL-ots). For 10 points, name this city\nwhere two lines of kings oversaw the cultivation of boys from age seven into full-time soldiers.",
      "answer": "Sparta"
    },
    {
      "question": "These people displaced an Iron Age culture known as the Villanovans. These people\nworshipped gods including Tin, Uni, and Cel, and they spoke a now-lost language whose last\nknown speaker was the Roman emperor Claudius. They legendarily provided the final three\nkings of Rome. For 10 points, name these pre-Roman inhabitants of the central Italian peninsula.",
      "answer": [
        "Etruscans"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This figure was guarded by a group of horsemen called the Celeres, and he may be associated with\nthe war god Quirinus because of his disappearance near the Quirinal Hill. He proclaimed “so perish every\none hereafter that will leap over my wall” while killing his brother after they debated the meaning of the\nnumber of birds flying around their heads. For ten points, name this brother of Remus, the first king of\nthe Romans.",
      "answer": "Romulus"
    },
    {
      "question": "Carlo Maderno expanded the nave of a building in this city. A fountain in this city includes a dove\nrepresenting the Pamphili family atop an Egyptian obelisk that overlooks the fountain’s depiction of four\nrivers. An amphitheatre in this city was built during the Flavian dynasty near the site of chariot racing at\nthe Circus Maximus. For ten points, name the city that contains St. Peter’s Basilica and the Colosseum.",
      "answer": "Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "This civilization’s early kings include two of the same name nicknamed “the fisherman” and “the\nshepherd.” Its first king, Alulim, ruled for 28,800 years according to its “King List,” written in cuneiform,\nan early form of writing developed in this civilization. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian civilization\nhome to the cities of Lagash and Ur, whose mythical king, Gilgamesh, is also on the King List.",
      "answer": [
        "Sumeria",
        "Sumer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person proclaimed “O Time, O traditions” in delivering a speech to fend off the Catiline\nConspiracy. His hands were placed on the Rostrum and Fulvia pierced this man’s tongue with a hairpin\nafter he was beheaded on the orders of Marc Antony, whom he had insulted in orations inspired by\nDemosthenes [deh-MOSS-theh-nees]. For ten points, name this famous Roman orator of the Philippics.",
      "answer": [
        "Marcus Tullius Cicero",
        "Cicero"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This person came to power after his wife ran over her father’s body with a chariot on the Vicus\nSceleratus. This person obtained the Sibylline Books from the Cumaean Sibyl. He allied with Lars Porsenna\nto try to regain power after Lucius Junius Brutus’s forces drove him out due to public indignation when\nhis son, Sextus, raped Lucretia. For ten points, name this successor to Servius Tullius, the last king of\nRome.",
      "answer": [
        "Tarquinius Superbus",
        "Tarquin the Proud"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s wife Vibia Sabina may have had an affair with his secretary, the historian\nSuetonius. He made Marcius Turbo Praetorian Prefect and employed the frumentarii as secret\npolice. This third of the Five Good Emperors was succeeded by Antoninus Pius. For 10 points,\nname this Roman emperor who demarcated the northern limit of Roman Britain with his\nnamesake wall.",
        "answer": [
          "Hadrian",
          "Publius Aelius Hadrianus Augustus",
          "Hadrianus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hadrian’s construction of the Aelia Capitolina caused a 132 A.D. revolt directed by\nthis Simon bar Kokhba, a member of this religious group.",
        "answer": [
          "Jews",
          "Jewish",
          "Judaism"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s former troops revolted against it in the Mercenary War. As a result, this city's\nleader Hanno the Great was displaced by the rising Barcid dynasty, whose members included\nHamilcar and Hasdrubal. This city lost the Battle of Zama to Scipio Africanus. For 10 points\nname this ancient North African city which was defeated by Rome in three Punic Wars.",
        "answer": "Carthage"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The site of Carthage is in which present day African country, whose soccer team is\nthus known as the Carthage Eagles?",
        "answer": "Tunisia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A powerful official in this government was the \"censor,\" who determined eligibility for the\nSenate. Politicians under this government followed the \"cursus honorum\" to move through the\nranks of aedile (pr. EY-dial), quaestor (pr. KWAI-stor), praetor (pr. PRAI-tor), and finally\nbecome one of two consuls. For 10 points, name this governmental system which was replaced\nby the Empire.",
        "answer": "Roman Republic, Republic"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A legendary censor was the \"elder\" man of what name, who was also known for ending\nhis speeches in the Senate by declaring \"Carthage must be destroyed?\"",
        "answer": "Cato"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Following this battle, Locris and Phocia (pr. FOH-see-uh) \"Medized\" (pr. MEED-eyzd). This\nbattle ended after Ephialtes (pr. eph-FYE-ull-TEEZ) showed the \"goat path\" to the winning\nforce, commanded by Xerxes (pr. ZERK-seez). For 10 points, name this 480 BC battle in which\nLeonidas (pr. LEE-oh-NYE-duss) led three hundred Spartans in holding a pass for three days\nagainst Persia.",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Thermopylae",
          "Thermopylae"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Also present at Thermopylae were troops from what city, which used the Sacred Band to\ncome to prominence in the fourth century BC and was the legendary home of Oedipus (pr. ED-uhpuss)?",
        "answer": "Thebes"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire was attacked by Croesus (pr. CREE-sus) of Lydia after the Delphic Oracle said\nthat \"a great empire will fall.\" This empire relied on local satraps who were loyal to emperors\nsitting at Susa. For 10 points, name this empire founded by Cyrus the Great, which launched a\nnamesake series of wars on Greece at the start of the fifth century BC.",
        "answer": [
          "Persian Empire",
          "Persia",
          "Achaemenid Empire",
          "Achaemenid"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which Persian Emperor lost at Issus and Gaugamela, and was the third to hold this\nname?",
        "answer": "Darius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This system was restored following the overthrow of Hippias (pr. HIP-ee-uss), after which its\ncentral feature was the boulé (pr. BOO-lay). This system involved citizens being arranged into\ndemes (pr. DEEMZ) by Cleisthenes (pr. CLICE-thuh-neez). For 10 points, identify this\npolitical system used in classical Athens, which inspired similar vote-based systems in the\nmodern world.",
        "answer": [
          "Athenian democracy",
          "democracy"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Members of the boulé were selected by what method, also used to pick the tenth of an\narmy that Romans \"decimated\" and the date of the massacre of Jews in the Book of Esther?",
        "answer": [
          "by drawing of lots",
          "lots"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “Our constitution does not copy the laws of neighboring states” in a speech\nthat offered “comfort [...], not condolence” after the first year of the Archidamian War. He evacuated the\nfarmers of Attica to within the Long Walls, which protected them from Spartan skirmishes but led to the\nspread of plague that killed him. For ten points, name this statesman of the Athenian Golden Age who\nopposed Sparta in the early Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Pericles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pericles’ 431 BC oration commemorating the first year of the Peloponnesian War was given at\nwhat type of event?",
        "answer": "funeral"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During a drunken brawl, this man killed his officer Cleitus the Black, who had earlier saved this\nman’s life during the Battle of the Granicus River. This man’s successors were known as the Diadochi\n[dee-AH-doh-kee], and this rider of Bucephalus defeated Darius III at the Battle of Gaugamela. For ten\npoints, name this son of Phillip II, a king of Macedon who conquered Persia.",
        "answer": "Alexander the Great"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander the Great was tutored as a youth by this man, who established the Lyceum and wrote\nNicomachean Ethics.",
        "answer": "Aristotle"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "These entities were controlled through “ingenuity” among other things, utilizing both a mahout and\na howdah. Among the most famous use of this weapon was at the Battle of the Hydaspes River by King\nPorus against Alexander the Great. Hannibal baffled the Romans by crossing the Alps with them. For ten\npoints, name this animal, akin to an ancient tank, which is now hunted for its ivory tusks.",
        "answer": [
          "elephants"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander’s victory over King Porus at the Hydaspes required one of these military maneuvers,\nalso performed by Julius Caesar - albeit with no immediate enemy - at the Rubicon.",
        "answer": [
          "river crossing",
          "river cross"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Supposedly, prior to this battle, Cyrsillus and his wife were stoned for suggesting surrender. Washed\nup sailors were slaughtered on Psyttaleia [sit-uh-LYE-uh] by Aristides [air-uh-STY-dees], and a throne\nwas erected for the losing commander to watch the battle. This battle vindicated the “wooden walls”\nof Themistocles, who advocated abandoning Athens prior to this battle. The battles of Artemisium and\nThermopylae were fought prior to, for ten points, what naval battle, a victory for the allied Greeks over\nXerxes I?",
        "answer": [
          "Battle of Salamis",
          "Salamis"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One commander under Xerxes was Queen Artemisia of this place, which was also the birthplace\nof Herodotus and the site of a notable mausoleum.",
        "answer": "Halicarnassus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Gaius Suetonius Paulinus put down a revolt on this island by the Trinovantes and the Iceni\n[ee-KAY-nee] at the Battle of Watling Street. The northern limit of the Roman Empire on this island\nwas once marked by Hadrian’s Wall, built sixty years after Boudica sacked its city of Londinium. For ten\npoints, name this island, now home to the countries of Wales, Scotland, and England.",
        "answer": [
          "Great Britain",
          "Britain",
          "Brittania"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Britain was home to the Picts, who lived north of this Scottish river on which Edinburgh lies.",
        "answer": [
          "River Forth",
          "Forth",
          "Firth of Forth"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s head was immersed in a jar of blood by Queen Tomyris to satisfy his bloodlust. This\nmonarch used camels to win the Battle of Thymbra, defeating Croesus of Lydia. His capture of Babylon\nis detailed in his namesake Cylinder, and Isaiah refers to him as a messiah for his freeing the Jews from\nthe Babylonian Captivity. The satrapy system was created by, for ten points, what first Achaemenid ruler\nof the Persian empire?",
        "answer": [
          "Cyrus the Great",
          "Cyrus II"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Aside from the Cylinder, most of what is known of Cyrus’ reign comes from what “father of\nhistory,” who traced the origins of the Greco-Persian War in his Histories?",
        "answer": "Herodotus"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city was ruled by dual kings from the Agiad and Eurypontid dynasties, who were responsible to\nthe ephors. One ruler of this city, Lycurgus the Lawgiver, introduced the agoge [ah-goh-gah], a rigorous\ntraining program for all young men. One king of this city replied “come and take them” after being asked\nto lay down his arms by Xerxes I. Leonidas died at Thermopylae with 300 soldiers from, for ten points,\nwhat militaristic Greek city-state, a rival of Athens?",
        "answer": "Sparta"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Spartan farms were primarily worked by these slaves, who were primarily conquered Messalians.",
        "answer": "helots"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city’s ruins held the Plimpton 322 tablet, which lists a series of Pythagorean triples. A 7th\nand 6th century BC empire based in this city grew under Nabopolassar and ended when Nabondius was\ndefeated by Cyrus the Great. The Hittites defeated an older empire in this city, which instituted a law\ncode based on the “eye for an eye” concept. For ten points, name this Mesopotamian city-state led in\ndifferent millennia by Hammurabi and Nebuchadnezzar, who built the Hanging Gardens there.",
        "answer": [
          "Babylon",
          "Neo-Babylonian Empire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "These Mesopotamian step-pyramids had shrines at their highest levels. Nabonidus rebuilt a\nGreat one of these in Ur.",
        "answer": "ziggurats"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FAMOUS GREEKS",
      "prompt": "What person or god from ancient Greece...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of the Olympian gods and was depicted in a famous statue at Olympia?",
          "answer": "Zeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran naked through the streets of Syracuse shouting \"Eureka\" after discovering buoyancy?",
          "answer": "Archimedes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a cult which opposed eating beans and discovered a side length theorem for right\ntriangles?",
          "answer": "Pythagoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the \"gadfly of Athens\" whose Apology was recorded by Plato?",
          "answer": "Socrates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Offered a salt spring as a gift to Athens, which then chose Athena as its patron deity instead?",
          "answer": "Poseidon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the first book of history, The Persian Wars?",
          "answer": "Herodotus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was called the \"tenth muse\" for her accomplishments as a female poet on Lesbos?",
          "answer": "Sappho"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a \"funeral oration\" on Athenian ideals during the Peloponnesian War?",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT INDIA",
      "prompt": "In classical India, what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Nirvana-focused religion founded by Siddhartha Gautama?",
          "answer": [
            "Buddhism",
            "Buddhist"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Language ancestral to modern Hindi that was used to write ancient Hindu texts?",
          "answer": "Sanskrit"
        },
        {
          "question": "Number first articulated in fifth-century India during the invention of decimals?",
          "answer": [
            "zero",
            "shunya"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "River at which Indian civilization grew near the city of Varanasi?",
          "answer": "Ganges"
        },
        {
          "question": "Macedonian general who reached the borders of India with his conquests?",
          "answer": [
            "Alexander the Great",
            "Alexander"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Treatise on the art of love composed around the second century AD?",
          "answer": [
            "Kama Sutra",
            "Kamasutra"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Epic about the king of Ayodha (pr. eye-OH-duh) defeating the demon Ravana?",
          "answer": "the Ramayana"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dynasty in power from 322 to 185 BC, whose emperors included Asoka (pr. uh-SHOWkuh)?",
          "answer": [
            "Mauryan dynasty",
            "Maurya",
            "Mauryan empire"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CLEOPATRA",
      "prompt": "Cleopatra VII was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The last Macedonian pharaoh of what land prior to its conquest by Rome?",
          "answer": "Egypt"
        },
        {
          "question": "The mother of a child whose father was what Ides of March assassination victim?",
          "answer": [
            "Julius Caesar",
            "Caesar",
            "Gaius Julius Caesar"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Later the partner of what Second Triumvirate member who fought with Octavian?",
          "answer": [
            "Mark Antony",
            "Marcus Antonius",
            "Antony",
            "Antonius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The daughter, sister, and mother of men with what dynastic name?",
          "answer": "Ptolemy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The loser of what 31 BC naval battle which sealed her fate?",
          "answer": [
            "Battle of Actium",
            "Actium"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Killed, in some versions, when she allowed what kind of snake to bite her?",
          "answer": "asp"
        },
        {
          "question": "Presented to her first Roman lover inside what object?",
          "answer": [
            "rolled-up carpet",
            "rug"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Able to fulfill a vow to serve a ten-million-sesterces dinner by serving what item dissolved in\nvinegar?",
          "answer": [
            "pearls"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MESOPOTAMIA",
      "prompt": "Mesopotamia...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Means “land between the rivers” in what ancient language spoken in Corinth and Athens?",
          "answer": [
            "Ancient Greek",
            "Greek"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the birthplace of what practice, including irrigation, that allowed hunter-gatherers to settle?",
          "answer": [
            "agriculture",
            "farm",
            "farming"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to the Hanging Gardens in what city?",
          "answer": "Babylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used what wedge-shaped form of writing?",
          "answer": "cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the eastern part of a region known by what two-word term, named for its shape and arable land?",
          "answer": "Fertile Crescent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was located between what two rivers that flow to the Persian Gulf?",
          "answer": [
            "Tigris and Euphrates Rivers",
            "Tigris and Euphrates"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was primarily located in what modern-day country, whose cities include Mosul and Basra?",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to what city, whose Great Ziggurat was excavated by Leonard Woolley?",
          "answer": "Ur"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "ANCIENT GREEK WARFARE",
      "prompt": "In Ancient Greece, who or what was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The Greek god of war?",
          "answer": "Ares"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city in Asia Minor legendarily sacked by Greek troops after the abduction of Helen?",
          "answer": "Troy"
        },
        {
          "question": "The militaristic rival of Athens led by Leonidas?",
          "answer": "Sparta"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Boetian city represented by the Sacred Band?",
          "answer": "Thebes"
        },
        {
          "question": "The city that dominated the isthmus connecting the Peloponnese to mainland Greece and was the\ncenter of a League led by Philip II?",
          "answer": "Corinth"
        },
        {
          "question": "The battle formation of rows of spear-bearing hoplites whose name comes from the Greek for\n“fingers”?",
          "answer": "Phalanx"
        },
        {
          "question": "The wooden ships with three banks of oars that formed the “Wooden Wall” of Athens?",
          "answer": [
            "Triremes"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "The 479 BCE land battle where the Greeks killed the Persian general Mardonius?",
          "answer": "Plataea"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "AUGUSTUS CAESAR",
      "prompt": "Augustus Caesar...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the first holder of what position, after Rome had spent centuries as a republic?",
          "answer": [
            "Emperor of Rome",
            "Emperor"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was known by what birth name prior to taking that position?",
          "answer": [
            "Gaius Octavian",
            "Octavian",
            "Gaius Octavius",
            "Octavius"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a member of what political alliance with Marcus Lepidus and Marc Antony?",
          "answer": "Second Triumvirate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won the Battle of Philippi against what partner of Cassius?",
          "answer": [
            "Marcus Junius Brutus",
            "Brutus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cried out for Varus to give him back what units, a standard military division in Rome?",
          "answer": "legions"
        },
        {
          "question": "Personally owned what region south of the Mediterranean, the source of much of Rome’s grain?",
          "answer": [
            "Egypt",
            "Aegyptus"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Held what other title, which translates to “first citizen?”",
          "answer": [
            "Princeps civitatis",
            "Princeps"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Relied on what trusted admiral and son-in-law who commissioned the Pantheon?",
          "answer": [
            "Marcus Vipsanius Agrippa",
            "Agrippa"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The latest date for this facility's destruction is 642, according to the story blaming Amr ibn\nal As, though it is also believed that Theophilus ordered it (20 pts) ",
        "burned in 391 or that it fell\nvictim to the chaos of the Zenobia revolt. This building housed thousands of (10 pts) ",
        "scrolls and\ntablets and was the jewel of a complex dedicated to the Muses by Ptolemy (pr. TAH-luh-mee).\nFor 10 points, name this center of learning in the Classical world, which was found in Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Library of Alexandria"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2003, this person was identified as the \"Younger Queen\" mummy by the minority\nfaction of archaeologists which holds that she was the same person as the pharaoh (20 pts) ",
        "Smenkhkare. Berlin's Neues (NOY-iss) Museum currently holds a famous (10 pts) ",
        "bust of this\nperson, which is traditionally attributed to a sculptor known as Thutmose. For 10 points, name\nthis wife of Akhenaten who might have preceded Tutankhamun as pharaoh of Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": "Nefertiti"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Livy claims that one participant in this conflict used heated vinegar to cross a blocked\nmountain pass. Quintus Fabius was nicknamed “the delayer” during this conflict for refusing\nto engage in battle. One side in this conflict lost at (20 pts) ",
        "Lake Trasimene [trah-sih-meh-nee]\nbut later won the decisive victory on the plains of Zama under Scipio [SKIP-ee-oh],\ncounteracting a devastating loss at Cannae [CANN-aye]. The (10 pts) ",
        "Alps were traversed by\nHannibal during, for ten points, what second of a series of conflicts between Rome and Carthage?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "2nd Punic War",
        "2nd Punic"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This man is depicted with his wife in the Coregency Stela. Burnaburiash asked\nthis man for gold and Tushratta wished him well in a set of correspondences named\nfor this man’s capital, (20 pts) ",
        "Amarna. This founder of a (10 pts) ",
        "monotheistic religion changed\nhis name to honor the new god. Nefertiti was the wife of, for ten points, what Egyptian ruler once\nknown as Amenhotep IV who began a monotheistic religion centered on the sun-disk, Aten?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Akhenaten",
        "Napkhuria"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Invading Elamites led this man to ally with rival city Larsa. He later overthrew King\nIsme-Dagan from power and his successor faced a rebellion led by Rim-Sin. This leader was\nheavily influenced by the concept of (20 pts) ",
        "lex talionis, or retributive justice, when writing a\nwork discovered on a black stele by Gustave Jequier. That stele depicts this man receiving a\nscroll from the god (10 pts) ",
        "Shamash and has an inscription of punishments for various crimes, including\n“an eye for an eye”. For ten points, name this Babylonian king whose law code is among the oldest\nrecovered writings."
      ],
      "answer": "Hammurabi"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A musician attempted to avenge his friend’s death by assassinating this ruler. In another\nincident, this man killed another would-be assassin who had hidden a dagger in a map. This\nman visited (20 pts) ",
        "Zhifu Island three times in attempts to gain immortality, but he died by\nswallowing mercury pills that were supposed to make him immortal. After his death, this\nleader was buried with (10 pts) ",
        "thousands of terracotta warriors. For ten points, name this first emperor\nof the Qin dynasty and of a unified China."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Qin Shi Huangdi",
        "Shi Huang"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The eunuch Pothinus tried to depose this ruler with help from Ptolemy XIII. This\nruler’s sister, Arsinoe IV, was killed in the Temple of Ephesus for being a perceived threat.\nThis ruler was legendarily (20 pts) ",
        "smuggled into a room in a rolled up carpet. Her children\nwere given significant land in the Donation of (10 pts) ",
        "Alexandria three years before she fled from the\nBattle of Actium, leading to her lover’s defeat by Augustus Caesar for control of the Roman Empire. For\nten points, name this lover of Mark Antony, the last pharaoh of an independent Egypt."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Cleopatra VII Philopator",
        "Cleopatra"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One structure on this island was built slightly north of the Stanegate and was near the\nMilitary Way. Julius Caesar made note of the (20 pts) ",
        "chariots used on this island during his\n55 BC invasion. Gaius Suetonius won the Battle of Watling Street on this island to defeat a\nrevolt of the Iceni led by (10 pts) ",
        "Boudicca. One structure on this island was built near Pictland as the\nnorthern border of the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this island, the site of Hadrian’s Wall and a\nRoman province with capital at Londinium, now known as London."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Britannia",
        "Britain",
        "British Isles",
        "British"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s forces were betrayed on a journey to Messina by his hired Cilician pirates;\nshortly after, he was denied a truce, then decisively beaten and killed at the Siler (20 pts) ",
        "River.\nA single man volunteered to lead an army to defeat this former murmillo; the practice of\nkilling every tenth soldier, or decimation, was reintroduced for discipline purposes by that\nvolunteer, (10 pts) ",
        "Crassus. After this leader lost the Third Servile War, his followers were crucified along\nthe Appian Way. For ten points, name this first century BC Greek soldier who led a failed slave revolt\nafter escaping captivity as a Roman gladiator."
      ],
      "answer": "Spartacus"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Prior to this battle, the winning commander sent Sicinnus to the opposing camp to fake\ntreason, drawing their forces into an arm of the Saronic Gulf. The losing commander at this\nbattle lamented “my (20 pts) ",
        "men have turned into women, my women men,” after he observed\nArtemisia of Halicarnassus ramming her own ally to escape. Athens was (10 pts) ",
        "abandoned prior\nto this battle, which vindicated the “wooden wall” navy built by Themistocles. For ten points, name this\n480 BC naval battle in which Xerxes’ Persian navy was crushed by a Greek alliance."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Battle of Salamis",
        "Salamis"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city is home to the Erechtheion, a temple probably designed by Mnesicles [neh-sihklees] and financially supported by the treasury of the (20 pts) ",
        "Delian League, which was based\nin this city. This city was connected to its port, several kilometers away at Piraeus, by the\nLong Walls, which were ordered destroyed in (10 pts) ",
        "404 BC after this city lost the Peloponnesian\nWar. For ten points, name this ancient Greek city-state where Pericles ordered the building of the\nParthenon on the Acropolis."
      ],
      "answer": "Athens"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Holders of this position possessed the Heirloom Seal of the Realm and ranked\ntheir consorts and concubines. The first holder of this position, a (20 pts) ",
        "Legalist, ended\nthe Warring States period, burned books, and was buried with an army of terracotta\nwarriors. The (10 pts) ",
        "Mandate of Heaven empowered, for ten points, what position held by Qin Shi\nHuangdi and hundreds of other Middle Kingdom leaders?"
      ],
      "answer": "Emperor of China"
    }
  ]
}